{"tossups": [{"question": "This group was the first target of Justinian\u2019s reconquest wars. These people, along with the Alans, were led by Genseric. These people captured Carthage in 439 AD, making it the capital of their North African empire. Pope Leo I was able to limit, but not stop, these people\u2019s 455 sack of Rome. For ten points, name this Germanic tribe whose name has become synonymous with defacing and destroying property.", "answer": "<b> Vandal</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In one scheme, this man attempted to negotiate a secret rebate with railroad companies by creating the South Improvement Company. A company founded by this man was subject of a muckraking expose by Ida Tarbell. This man grew his business through horizontal integration after establishing a series of refineries in Ohio, but his flagship company was eventually broken up by the Supreme Court in 1911. For ten points, name this founder of the Standard Oil company.", "answer": "John D.<b> Rockefeller</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2012, this country temporarily occupied the Heglig oil field of its northern neighbor. The President of this country has been known for his fondness for Stetson hats since he received one as a gift from George W. Bush in 2006. Civil war broke out in this country in 2013 shortly after Riek Machar was accused of plotting a coup d\u2019etat by President Salva Kiir. For ten points, name this African country that declared its independence in 2011.", "answer": "Republic of<b> South Sudan</b> (do not accept or prompt on Sudan alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One holder of this position, John Lindsay, switched parties to mount a failed bid for the Democratic nomination for President in 1972. Norman Mailer ran on an Existentialist Party ticket for this office. This office\u2019s occupants, including Fernando Wood, were often controlled by \u201cBoss\u201d Tweed and his Tammany Hall organization. For ten points, name this office held in more recent years by Rudy Giuliani, Michael Bloomberg, and Bill de Blasio.", "answer": "<b> Mayor</b> of<b> New York</b> City (accept<b> Mayor of NY</b>C)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Azizul Haque and Hem Chandra Bose subdivided these objects into 1024 types to develop the Henry Classification System of sorting them. Excavating pottery in Japan piqued Henry Fauld\u2019s interest in these objects. Marcello Malpighi documented friction ridges in these structures, which Francis Galton divided into loops, arches, and whorls. For ten points, forensic science studies the identification of what patterns that are unique to every human and often left at crime scenes?", "answer": "<b> fingerprint</b>s Page 1", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "A series of<em> Reflections on</em> this period were written by Edmund Burke. During this period, the seating arrangements in the National Assembly gave rise to the modern left-right political spectrum. This period led to the execution of thousands of Monarchists and Girondins during the Reign of Terror. Maximilien Robespierre came to prominence during, for ten points, what period of French history that toppled the monarchy?", "answer": "<b> French Revolution</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This leader, who introduced the aureus, is the subject of a lifesize marble sculpture found in Prima Porta in 1863. The Ara Pacis shows this leader in triumphal procession. This leader adopted the title of <em>divi filius</em> after gaining power 17 years after the murder of Julius Caesar. Along with Marc Antony and Lepidus, he formed the Second Triumvirate. For ten points, name this first emperor of Rome.", "answer": "<b> Augustus</b> Caesar (or<b> Octavian</b>; accept Gaius Julius Caesar<b> Augustus</b>; accept Gaius <b>Octavius</b> Thurinus; prompt on Caesar; do not prompt on Julius Caesar) (9) A banker and a judge who helped draft this treaty were nicknamed the \u201cheavenly twins.\u201d Polish pianist Ignacy Paderewski served as a delegate to this treaty, which left the status of the Teschen district unresolved and demanded the transfer of the regions of Eupen-Malmedy and Saar. This treaty was supervised by the \u201cBig Four\u201d, including Vittorio Orlando, Georges Clemenceau, and David Lloyd George. For ten points, name this peace treaty with Germany that ended World War I. ANSWER: Treaty of<b> Versailles</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "For ten points, name this landmark first reached by Captain Robert Peary, who traveled with several Inuit guides.", "answer": "<b> North Pole</b> Page 2", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Joseph von Eybler and Franz Sussmayr worked to complete an unfinished work by this composer. A legend claims that a masked man, working on behalf of Franz von Walsegg, commissioned that piece from this composer, who became convinced he was writing it for his own funeral. This composer completed work on<em> The Magic Flute</em> a few months before his 1792 death in Vienna. For ten points, name this Austrian composer who first gained fame as a child prodigy.", "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus<b> Mozart</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In response to this court case, Harry Byrd helped propose the doctrine of \u201cmassive resistance\u201d. This decision\u2019s use of the phrase \u201cwith all deliberate speed\u201d meant that its provisions were not implemented in some places for decades. Kenneth and Mamie Clark\u2019s experiments with dolls were used as evidence in this case, whose finding was enforced despite Orval Faubus\u2019s resistance at Little Rock Central High School. For ten points, name this Supreme Court decision that ordered the desegregation of public schools.", "answer": "<b> Brown</b> v. Board of Education of Topeka, Kansas BONUS:<em> Brown v. Board</em> partially overturned this 1896 Supreme Court case, which developed the concept\u201cseparate but equal\u201d accommodations. ANSWER:<b> Plessy</b> v. Ferguson", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This city was the northern terminus of the Natchez Trace. To commemorate the 1897 World\u2019s Fair, this American city constructed a full-scale replica of the Parthenon. Directly east of this city lies an estate called the Hermitage that was the longtime residence of Andrew Jackson. This city on the southern stretch of the Cumberland River contains Music Row and the Country Music Hall of Fame. For ten points, name this capital and most populous city in Tennessee.", "answer": "<b> Nashville</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This country suffered an outburst of violence known as the<em> sacudon</em> in 1989 after the election of the rightist president Carlos Andres Perez. One president of this country ran the TV show<em> Alo Presidente</em>, initiated a program in which this country supplied oil to Caribbean states, and inaugurated a government he called a \u201cBolivarian Republic.\u201d For ten points, name this country once led by Hugo Chavez.", "answer": "Bolivarian Republic of<b> Venezuela</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During one of this country\u2019s independence struggles, Jean-Henri Dunant established the International Red Cross after witnessing the Battle of Solferino. In 1860, the Spanish Bourbons were ousted by the Expedition of the Thousand, ensuring the success of this country\u2019s Risorgimento. For ten points, name this country that was unified under Victor Emmanuel II after the 1870 capture of Rome.", "answer": "<b> Italy</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Samuel Whitside intercepted a group led by Spotted Elk and forced them to encamp at this location. When the deaf Black Coyote refused to surrender his rifle at this location, members of the 7th US Cavalry opened fire. For ten points, name this creek in the Pine Ridge Reservation of South Dakota where, in 1890, hundreds of Lakota Sioux were killed in the largest domestic massacre in American history.", "answer": "<b> Wounded Knee</b> Creek (accept<b> Wounded Knee</b> Massacre; prompt on South Dakota and/or Pine Ridge Reservation and/or Lakota Sioux territory before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Correspondence from this era of history is mapped in a digital project by Dan Edelstein called the Republic of Letters. Immanuel Kant held Frederick II as a ruler typical of this era in his essay \u201cWhat is [the word that names this era].\u201d A major project in this era comprised of over 70,000 articles; that work was partially compiled by d\u2019Alembert and known as the<em> Encyclopedie</em>. Voltaire was a major figure of, for ten points, what philosophical era largely in the 18th century that challenged religious, social, and political establishments by stressing the use of reason?", "answer": "<b> Enlightenment</b> (accept le<b> si`ecle des lumi`eres</b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This city was defended by a defensive ring called the Stelling, which overlooked the Zuiderzee. This city\u2019s Grachtengordel neighborhood is a UNESCO World Heritage site. The</b> <b>world\u2019s oldest (+)</b> <b>stock exchange is located in this city, where Rembrandt\u2019s</b><em><b> The Night</b></em> <b>stock exchange is located in this city, where Rembrandt\u2019s</b><em><b> The Night</b></em> <em><b>Watch</b></em><b> is located in the (*)</b> <em><b>Watch</b></em><b> is located in the (*)</b> Rijksmuseum [rikes-\u201dmuseum\u201d]. A famous resident of this city was sent to Bergen Belsen after a raid on the \u201cSecret Annex.\u201d For ten points, name this capital city of the Netherlands.", "answer": "<b> Amsterdam</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Production of this foodstuff requires nixtamalization [nish-tamal-ization], a soak-and-boil process using a very alkaline solution, to allow it to release nutrients and be more easily</b> <b>digested. That process was developed around 1500 BC and creates (+)</b> <b>hominy, which can</b> <b>hominy, which can</b> <b>be ground into masa flour and dough. This grain was first domesticated in (*)</b> <b>be ground into masa flour and dough. This grain was first domesticated in (*)</b> southern Mexico and, with beans and squash, was one of the Three Sisters of Native American agriculture. For ten points, name this grain crop that is also known as maize.", "answer": "<b> corn</b> (accept any type of<b> corn</b>; accept<b> hominy</b> and/or<b> masa</b> before they are mentioned; accept<b> maize</b> before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This author wrote about two brothers who flip a coin to determine which one of them will join the Jacobite Rebellion of 1745 in his novel</b><em><b> The Master of Ballantrae</b></em><b>. In a novel by</b> <b>this author, Alan Breck Stewart joins forces with (+)</b> <b>David Balfour, who had been sold</b> <b>David Balfour, who had been sold</b> <b>to a group of passing mariners by his uncle. In another book by this man, the (*)</b> <b>to a group of passing mariners by his uncle. In another book by this man, the (*)</b> pirate Long John Silver leads the search for a buried gold. For ten points, name this author of<em> Kidnapped</em> and <em>Treasure Island</em>.", "answer": "Robert Louis<b> Stevenson</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>In 1864, two dozen unarmed Union soldiers were killed in this state\u2019s Centralia Massacre by a mob that included Jesse James. A governor of this state named Lilburn Boggs issued</b> <b>the \u201cextermination order\u201d against the (+)</b> <b>Mormon church. \u201cBorder ruffians\u201d migrated</b> <b>Mormon church. \u201cBorder ruffians\u201d migrated</b> <b>from this state into a neighboring one to promote slavery, and this state\u2019s cities of (*)</b> <b>from this state into a neighboring one to promote slavery, and this state\u2019s cities of (*)</b> St. Joseph and Independence were major starting points of trails leading to the West. For ten points, name this state where the Gateway Arch was built to celebrate St. Louis\u2019s role as a conduit to the West.", "answer": "<b> Missouri</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "When this country banned slavery, the law excluded its (*) </b> East India Company. Slavery was introduced to the colony of Australia by, for ten points, what country that ended the slave trade under Queen Victoria?", "answer": "<b> U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (accept Great<b> Britain</b>; accept<b> England</b>) ", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This policy exempted the Japanese, Koreans, and Taiwanese after the government</b> <b>that implemented it signed an export deal with Japan. This policy, which included</b> <b>passbook laws and the establishment of semi-independent (+)</b> <b>\u201chomelands,\u201d was</b> <b>implemented by the government of Hendrik Verwoerd. Under P. W. Botha, (*)</b> bantustans were founded as part of this policy, which ended in the early 1990s. For ten points, name this policy of racial discrimination in South Africa.", "answer": "<b> Apartheid</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}